[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio my
name is phil winston and my guest today
is philip mayhew
phil is a co-founder and the cto at
gamedriver a company that brings test
automation to the video game industry
before game driver he ran his own
consultancy for over a decade which
specialized in performance and
functional test automation for fortune
500 companies phil did i leave anything
out of your bio that you wanted to add
phil that pretty much covers everything
i've uh you know just the early
background have a degree in computer
science from north carolina state
university
great
we're going to use the term game
throughout this episode
but i'd like to frame this in the
beginning and understand that we might
be talking about applications that are
wider than just games i've seen your
company use the term immersive
experience how would you describe the
set of applications we're going to be
talking about today what characteristics
do they have so you know of course our
name is dropped off of you know gaming
automation game driver but you know that
was we came up with that name you know
four years ago and and now as
the landscape has started to change with
augmented reality virtual reality where
you've got people learning how to you
know change a tire from an immersive
experience so
we now have this broader application
landscape that needs
automated testing so
it's not your classic we're just testing
games anymore we're testing all kinds of
industrial usages of the applications
that are being put out these days
so there are challenges to write
automated tests for any application
maybe we can talk a little bit about
those since your background prior to
game driver was in a wider field of
applications and then we can zoom in to
talking about the specific challenges
for games but to start why is test
automation hard
sure so
we can break this into two separate
categories we have
sort of an educational dilemma and then
we have you know technological problems
that have to be solved as well
so i like to compare
where game
testing automation is today
is very similar to where enterprise
application testing was automated
testing was 12 15 years ago
you have a lot of people who have been
doing
manual testing who are not familiar with
how to do automated testing so we need
to be able to empower those people to
you know write automated test cases and
implement those test cases so what are
some of the ways we can do that we can
do that through
training
and from a technological standpoint we
can empower them with tools in this case
we're using game driver to empower our
game testers to write automated test
cases that covers the you know the the
educational side of things from a
technological standpoint
when you're testing an enterprise
application
for you know functional automation
the buttons are generally in the same
location
text is you know very static we're
looking at a static 2d environment where
feedback is very specific on what a user
does
when you look at a 3d game i mean that's
a it's a completely different landscape
and
precision of points becomes an issue you
know if you move a control pad you know
a d-pad a little bit you know all right
so we're we're talking floating point
values now we're no longer talking
pixel exactness so now we're having to
deal with with those kinds of issues and
while it seems complex
you know
to write an automated test case for a
game
we're not trying to be able to
walk a character from start to finish
through a game how do we defeat the the
dragon to to get the key to save the
princess we don't have to have a complex
scenario
to be successful
there's an old enterprise application
you know automation thing you know it's
something like with twenty percent of
automation you can complete eighty
percent of your testing
so the you know the old 20 80. and
i don't know that we can successfully
draw that kind of comparison in game
testing now but you've gotta look at
defects that are raised you know by
testers or developers
and say hey you know
this is a reoccurring issue or this is
something
we could automate
easily and cut down some of our manual
testing time you know we're not trying
to wipe out manual testing
that's not the goal the goal is to save
time which saves money and we can do
that through
using tools in this instance game driver
to simplify the process of being able to
create
repeatable test cases that generate
repeatable results and with that we can
add confidence into the you know
regression testing or you know minimal
acceptance test suite that allows us to
have confidence that we're moving
forward in our
in our development life cycle and we're
not introducing a lot of issues or you
know finding funding issues that
we didn't know existed so sure there's
going to be plenty of edge cases that
are difficult to
automate out but there is a still a
large portion of testing that can be
automated and it can be done very simply
so one of the things you mentioned was
maybe to contrast enterprise software
and games and one aspect of that that i
was reading about is games used to
be sort of one and done that you'd ship
the game way back when on a cartridge or
a dvd and there weren't any updates
after that point and then we get through
a period where
the games are still
on standard media but maybe they're
updated bugs are fixed but i think now
we're reaching the point where many
games are sort of developed and
maintained indefinitely have you seen
that trend and how does that correlate
or impact
automated testing
i think that's uh that's a bit of an
ideological
question or dilemma that we have here
because if you look back and you know
i'm 40 years old now i remember having
windows 3.1 windows 95 i mean once you
installed that that was it
but with the the mainstream introduction
of always on internet
you know you're constantly getting
windows updates and it's not just games
that are doing this it's software across
the board
with your mobile devices it's so easy
for
developers to just push updates so i
think that it's a plus side is that you
know if we have an issue sure we can
easily fix it but
i wonder that it also
is limiting the testing that happens
because now that
you know we can say oh we can push an
update at any point
there's no need to necessarily spend as
much time testing a product and so
you know it's just getting pushed out
the door a lot sooner with hopes that
you know patches can can be pushed
downstream at a later point you know
we've recently seen in the news where
that
that has had
repercussions of you know detrimental
business results where people have said
you know we'll just push it out the door
and you know do updates later let me
mention a previous episode here it was
episode 339 with jafar sultani on
continuous delivery for multiplayer
games
and one of the comments he had was we
are heavily relying on an army of manual
testers to test the game but relative to
this idea of sort of a long-lived
application he mentioned that
once you sort of got rid of those manual
testers after the initial release or
they drifted off to other projects you
lost the confidence in being able to
even make small changes so i imagine
with automated testing one of the goals
is to give
developers the confidence is that an
objective that you see with your work
yeah i think so i mean it's
you can substitute
manual testers here with developers you
know a developer moves off a project and
what's gone well you know
across any you know the development
history of of software applications
retaining constantly updated and
up-to-date documentation has always been
a problem and so when you remove an
individual who has what seems like an
infinite space of knowledge in his head
to another project that information just
is gone
having
automated test cases as a way to
retain information and
documentation as a result of doing
automated testing so you know when uh
when a manual tester moves on a lot of
knowledge is gone with him and
so if we're taking some of that
knowledge and we're investing in
building automated test cases with it
when they go the developers can know all
right we still have this huge suite of
testing that's been done that we can
again execute
without having that guy's or that
person's knowledge that was specifically
doing the testing so i think that it's a
way of building documentation
without saying
sit down here and write out a bunch of
documents about what was tested and how
it's tested
and the developer can sit there and it's
not just going back through emails he
can specifically look at the test cases
that were written that were executed and
have some sense of confidence that we
already we have code coverage on this
and if we execute these tests and i make
a change here then
we can sort of have a feedback loop to
know and have confidence that we're not
introducing new braking changes and i
mean this is we're talking about games
here but that's no different than than
any other application that's being
developed and you know when when people
leave off a project how do we retain
confidence and what we're still pushing
out so in that previous episode there
was a lot of talk about unit testing and
they did have a lot of unit tests even
though they were still doing manual
testing so what is the difference what
is the line between unit testing and the
type of test automation you normally
deal with and does it have to do with
whether the entire application is
running or are there other factors
yeah so i think the difference there is
we also need to focus on
user input so that is a
when when it comes to game testing that
is a key component what is the user
doing on the game pad and how is that
impacting what's happening in the
environment
so what i've deemed are the two most
important parts of automated testing is
one
doing accurate inputs that would
simulate what a user is doing and two
how do we validate that so we've got a
input and then a
validation feedback loop to continue
to test what we're trying to test and
understand the results of that test so
while a developer has been very focused
on you know unit tests what specifically
is happening on this method execution or
in this class instantiation or whatever
it is and on the on the flip side of
that we've got
manual testers who are testing as this
is a black box they have no insight into
you know what objects are doing what
and they're only doing validation based
on visual cues
with the automated testing now we're
empowering them to be able to
enhance what they're validating all
right so
we push a button this block turns red
all right we see it's red
but let's validate that it is the
correct hue of red you know maybe you're
working on a a game that is for people
who are color blind
so when there's specific things that
need to be validated that aren't
necessarily easy for a manual tester to
do but it's very simple to do in an
automated fashion so to separate that
line i i think that we have to think
more about user input what it's driving
and focus less on the specifics on again
on unit testing all right that's that's
handled by the developer but now we're
we're an automated tester what can we do
to add value to our our testing life
cycle here okay one more question that's
kind of defining our terms and then
we're going to jump into sort of the
process of adding automated testing to a
project then we're going to talk about
game driver and we'll try to cover
everything so this last
defining our terms question was i saw
the term collision testing and that's
not a term that is normally used with
regular applications what is collision
testing and what difficulties does it
present in automation
so when games you know when you have
objects and games interacting collisions
happen sometimes they're important
sometimes they're not important and
as a manual tester it might be easy to
see
a collision happen you know you bump
into a wall can you actually move
through the wall or you know the physics
enable and you bounce off the wall
whatever whatever the game structure is
for that
we do have the ability to
sort of supplement from a testing
perspective you know how do we register
a collision is happening
and can we register
collisions are happening on specific
objects when certain events happen when
the user
bumps into a wall all right let's make
sure that the collision code is actually
kicking off and that something is
happening again those are those are very
very easy to do visually most of the
time or you know if you have very tiny
objects that are colliding maybe from a
visual perspective they're not easy to
do but what if from an automated
perspective we can
have some
sort of helpers that are available to
signify that yes the collision happened
and now we can you know build more
testing that's covering a huge
sweep of objects in different scenarios
that are that is where collision is very
important that we understand what's
happening so it we can build a huge data
set of you know
of collision interactions and and test
all those in a massive sweep of
automated testing without you know
having to sit there and look at an excel
sheet of you know 100 different things
of the collisions we got to test and
validate yeah so that does sound pretty
specific to games or simulations or i
guess vr
environments stuff like that so now
let's talk about automated testing in
terms of like we're adding it to our
project maybe what are some of the steps
we do what are some of the things to
watch out for
so
what is the desired impact of automated
testing on a project suppose the
software game project has minimal
automated testing and you're you're
going to help them ramp that up and
after a year or something they have a
lot of automated testing what
differences are you trying to
drive there
so from the beginning
i guess sort of a personal goal of mine
has been to
limit the impact that
implementing
our product has on being able to add
automated testing like you know i
we don't want you to change your
architecture of your game we don't want
to complicate builds we want to try to
be as lightweight and as simple as
possible so that you know it's less
things that
developers have to figure out to make
this work we want it to be very seamless
so in the beginning people are like i
think they get overwhelmed by like
you know what do we do you have too many
moving parts
so
i think one of the easiest ways to get
started is all right let's do something
very simple
usually when a game starts you know your
intro screen comes up and hit the start
button
so let's let's write a simple test case
that you know
we it starts your game it waits for the
object to appear that says you know
press start button and then we press
start
and then let's validate the correct
scene loads and
the game is ready to go and and whatever
you know state capacity is required to
identify that the game is ready and once
you get
once you get people to write up just a
simple test case it's like the wheels
start turning and they just you know
it's just coming to them because they've
been in their project they know more
about the game than we would
and as the wheels are turning they're
like oh wow we can do we can do this we
can do that
suddenly all the defects that they've
opened previously are just flashing up
in their in their mind and they're
thinking oh yeah now we can we could
automate that pretty easily we can test
that every time and you know one of our
first customers
i can't remember the running total but
you know it was uh last i heard i was
kind of blown away at how many test
cases that that they had written so it's
and you know it's it's like anything
else you know you you do a lot of hard
work maybe on a test case like how do we
do this but
now we can copy you know some of that
test case and we can reuse it over here
for doing something very similar it's
like you know it's like developing a
hard product you develop a piece of it
oh yeah now we can reuse that
and you know before you know it you're
just turning out test cases and
and i think there's probably at some
point you leave a proportional limit
where you're
you're creating more test cases than
might be adding value in some respect
but
it really opens the door once you get
past that initial hurdle of all right
let's get it installed let's add it to
the game all right how do we connect
everything together and once you get
past that it's you know the wheels are
turning developers are very excited
because now
it's taking a little bit of burden off
their shoulders and they're going to be
able to shift that back to
you know an automated test engineer
who's gonna help them figure this stuff
out and make it work yeah i've seen the
same thing with regular applications
once the framework is in place and once
everyone sees the
whether it's hooked up to ci or
whatever's reporting the test results
once you sort of see that process
it can grow from there so how about the
trade-offs of when to write tests in the
development process
i can imagine saying hey write them as
early as possible but especially with a
game you might be
iterating and changing the game a lot
could you end up
writing tests prematurely what have you
recommended or what do you see people
doing
yeah and i think this you know very
closely relates with them with
application i mean you've got if you get
testers in too early they're you know
they're writing test cases and then you
know maybe some development happens on
the back end and suddenly those test
cases are invalidated
it can become a very complex loop where
you've got you know people writing
requirements
and you know maybe the testers aren't
reviewing those requirements or unaware
of those requirements again you know
we're in we're manual testing right now
and those testers are probably not even
aware of requirements documents that are
being written
to determine how development's going to
be done so there is going to be some
delay there you're not going to be able
to throw testers in immediately
but i think as you know games are being
developed we need to be cognizant of all
right now we can do some automated
testing
so you know should we shift
how we're developing games a little bit
so that
we're opening up the opportunity to
start doing automated testing earlier
than we would normally throw a manual
tester in so we don't want to throw a
manual tester in or throw automated
testing in and raising a bunch of
defects which well yeah of course we
know that doesn't work and it's not
supposed to work and yeah we kind of you
know sort of fudge that right now and
it's gonna change anyway so don't open
defects on this stuff
so i think there's you know there's
gonna have to be a little bit of thought
process into all right are we developing
games in such a sense that also makes
sense to take advantage of automated
testing or any kind of testing at an
earlier stage and you know maybe maybe
big studios are already doing that to
bring manual testers in sooner to help
validate things i i can't really comment
to that but you know i think there's
there is the opportunity to test early
you know
people like to say you know let's fail
fast that's uh you know that's one of
the
going logics around there today
so
yes and no it's you know some
some opportunity may may exist to test
early and some opportunity may not exist
to test early but
testing early can be a good thing and it
can be a bad thing so
i think there is there's an argument for
both sides and i think there's ways to
make it work but you know whether that's
always an opportunity
you know maybe maybe not
so we've talked about this a little bit
but who is actually writing these
automated tests is there an opportunity
for manual testers to learn just enough
programming if they don't know it
already or does it require
a software engineer who's very
experienced what range of abilities or
backgrounds
can people have to write successful
automated tests
you know personally i think that's a
very interesting question because
in my opinion
you know if you look in the landscape
and you you know you when you're in
college and
you've got all these this younger
generation
who are huge gamers and you know they
the one thing they want oh what do you
want to do oh man i'd love to get into
you know working at a game studio
all right how do you do that well i
don't know you know i've created some of
my own games and i'm just you know i'll
just keep interviewing and hoping uh a
break into the industry
i think a lot of people know that that's
a that's a very tough thing to do and
what this actually does creates an
opportunity where people with
you know some development experience you
know fresh out of school
they learn testing
and they can implement these automated
tests pretty easily
because they they've you know taken
their own initiative to
learn how to use engines like unreal and
unity and
they understand the basics of game
design they're taking game design
classes
in college they they may have taken some
testing classes as well
but we have this you know huge
population
and i say younger but you know there's
also older people who have just been
doing development who have always wanted
to do game development but you know it's
hard to break into the
game development scene on a larger scale
and
this opens up an opportunity for them to
learn a lot how the underlying games are
being developed
they're able to
understand that they're able to
write test cases for this i mean if you
look at if you look at application
testing to date you know
test cases and again like i said before
you know we're not writing comprehensive
ai's to go from start to finish of a
game we're just trying to
you know write simple test cases that
perform actions and we validate what
those actions are doing so we have you
know a huge population of people who are
technologically and developmentally
capable of writing these test cases and
it's going to give them the opportunity
to you know
sort of try to break into the industry
because they're now a part of the
development community of games and
this you know it's offering an
opportunity for them that they might not
have previously had i've talked to uh
you know a fair amount of people have
we've been hiring employees you know
they're they're manual testers and games
they've they have some development
experience
and they want to be game developers but
they haven't broken into the industry so
this is going to open up doors for
people to
have a chance to get a foot into that
industry i believe and
as the
i think the game automated testing
industry continues to grow it's going to
offer a lot of job opportunities for
people i mean
at the end of the day we want to we want
to be able to provide a tool that
is creating an underlying industry that
allows people to
get jobs train up
learn expertise
and i think that's going to gonna gonna
start to happen you know you probably
have a lot of manual testers
we're always gonna need manual testers
so if you have somebody who's not
necessarily the you know is willing to
sit down and learn how to write code but
you know writes great testing
documentation and we're still going to
need manual testers that are not going
away so there's still a lot of
opportunity for that and
we're creating tutorials we're creating
videos and we want to continue to
empower people to to learn how to do
this and i think you know there's going
to be third parties who are writing
blogs on how to do this stuff and if we
just want to see the industry continue
to grow
and
you know get to where enterprise
application testing is where most of
your testers can sit down and write
automated tests and i think that's going
to be a
a real boom for the industry yeah i can
see it's making sort of an on-ramp where
people can incrementally
develop their skills i think that's
really interesting to think about the
life cycle of someone's career and just
the growth so we talked a little bit
about what that first test is
checking that the start screen comes up
but let's say we have an existing
application without any real automated
tests how do we come up with a list of
the things that are going to be testable
with automation versus what do you stay
away from and say hey we're not going to
tackle that so maybe rather than the
first day this is like the first three
months or something i think a good
starting point is as implementing mats
which is
minimal acceptance test suite of a test
suite which we have some minimal
criteria that we need to ensure happens
every time
you know maybe the start screen is one
something like
can we create a new character once we
start the game can we save the game
i think starting with just you know some
simple
but crucial tests that we execute every
time
you know we we look at our our manual
testers spreadsheet or you know list of
tests that we are executing every time
right which of these are going to be
quick and simple and powerful so we can
implement those
let's also
reflect some of our high priority
defects that have been opened in the
past and ascertain whether you know we
should create some automated testing
around that because you know maybe
that's some
fragile code that we have in there that
we've run into problems where things
break that
as an outsider
looking at a game i can't necessarily
answer that
for a specific game but a developer
who's worked on that game
those things are going to pop right out
to them you know it's going to be very
obvious for them
probably same for the for manual testers
like you know every build we get this
thing is broken
or a piece of it doesn't work and you
know these are these are quick wins and
you know every time a manual test dress
open a defect for something it's burning
time it's burning cycles burning hours
that you know burning dollars they could
have if we can automate it run it
automate the you know opening of a
defect for it you know we're saving time
anytime we can save time
it's a win so
i think that's a good opportunity in the
you know first one to three months of
let's get some wins out there
so when are these tests being run is
seems uh most likely you have them
running during your ci your continuous
integration is that the answer that's
where these automated tests run or are
there other possibilities
i think we're gonna we're probably gonna
see a mix uh definitely the ci cd
pipeline is is a good good integration
point this is no different than any
other application testing you know you
let's say you're using jenkins for
instance you
have jenkins killed off kick off your
build pipeline and then after
build a successful all right let's let's
run our you know our automated test
suite and see what happens
we also have the ability for developers
who are working on something to say all
right i'm going to want to check in this
code but before i check in this code let
me review the automated tests you know
maybe i don't want to necessarily commit
the code and wait for the automated you
know build process to happen and and an
integrated testing gap and let's say i
want to
you know go ahead and just sort of test
that manually on on my machine run the
test suite before i check any code in so
i think there's going to be opportunity
between you know sitting here at your
desk and executing some test cases and
writing test cases
as opposed to you know
adding it into the build pipeline you
know your automated test engineer is
going to literally have to sit there and
test as he's as he's writing these test
cases as well so it's going to be
happening in two different places
it's almost as integrated test cases
have been kicked off sort of become a
regression because as we're writing
these we're also testing these test
cases as well
when a test fails what does the
developer want to see so they have a
name for the test and i guess sometimes
the test names can be long and maybe
descriptive and they get
a red indicator that it's failed
what else do they
need in order to then
debug the issue or fix fix the problem
so there's a couple things here
we of course in our product we've added
the ability to capture screenshots so
you know if a test case fails well let's
let's grab a screenshot of what happened
you know something more comprehensive
may come down the road where you want a
video of of what happened and
a log of what happened so we have our
what we executed in our test case is
essentially our log there but also you
know like in unity let's save off a copy
of that log because you know it probably
has some more information as well
so it's a combination of things of you
know your typical
no different than if a manual tester did
it except you know we're adding some
automated capability of of grabbing a
screenshot of wealth of what happened
you know there's unity again i'm just
could be unreal as well but unity you
know one of the partners companies that
we work with backtrace is also you know
collecting logs on on failures so i
think there's a combination of tooling
we don't want to necessarily
be responsible for
everything you know we're trying to fill
a specific part in the ecosystem and
integrate with other tools who are
focused and are the expertise and doing
that other part so you know it's no
different than tracking any other defect
i believe
invent your future at caci a national
security company revolutionizing
technology through digital c4 isr
cyber space
engineering and i.t transformations
you'll deliver information dominance
through the development of next
generation solutions at caci you'll be
treated like the company's greatest
asset when a company believes their
people are their greatest asset they let
the fest do what they do best
visit
careers.caci.com innovate to explore
caci's engineering and i.t opportunities
one more general question and then we'll
really dive into game driver specifics
what about performance testing i know
again your background prior to game
driver you did a lot with performance
tests is that a different breed of tests
than a functional automated test or is
it just another type of test you'd
include i guess the question is what
specific to performance testing does one
have to consider when making an
automated test
so in the you know i started doing
performance testing 15 years ago and
you know we're talking
purely at the you know at the protocol
level right so if you have a web
application you know where we're sending
that http traffic over and we're
measuring the response of of the
application and with the massive
multiplayer online games now you know
you still need to
test all that underlying architecture
and as testing has changed from a
performance standpoint you know we still
do a lot of the protocol level stuff but
also where you know people started
spinning up these different types of
tests where
we're not just simulating a bunch of
users but we're spawning you know a
thousand browser instances
so we
we've got two different types of
performance testing that are happening
in our web-based applications and the
same could be said from a client
perspective however
when you're
performance testing a game you know it's
not just a lightweight browser page
you've got a
huge resource consumption that is
happening on the game which is
essentially the client itself so it's i
think we're still gonna have to retain
our classic performance testing where
we're doing protocol level testing to
our server architecture
and we're not necessarily spawning up a
thousand game instances to drive
performance testing through an
automation framework that's interesting
i wasn't really thinking of the back end
of the game but that's
more like a normal web application where
the front end is the graphical so i
guess to be clear
now we can start talking about game
driver in particular do you write tests
for the back end as well as the
graphical client or the game driver is
focused exclusively on the graphical
part so you know the power of reflection
and unity we have the capability of
doing both
so that's you know one of the advantages
you know sorry my classic performance
test misinterpreted your question but
yeah when you're thinking you know
frames per second how well is the client
performing so yeah you know all that all
that is very pertinent information
i think a lot of that is is still gonna
you know they're still gonna be manual
testing and you know identifying whether
a game feels slow so our our agent is
yes very lightweight
and we've you know looked at ways to
continue to mitigate that it's not
impacting you know frames per second
so that you know even if you're running
an automated test we can still you know
pull the frames per second and make sure
that the game is you know is functioning
from a performance perspective without
you know worrying about the impact of
what we're doing game driver works with
unity today can you speak a little bit
about unity's role in the game ecosystem
why it was chosen as your first game
engine to work with and just a little
bit about unity yeah so the
before me so
my other two founders rob and shane who
were friends before we started the
company
wanted to get into game development and
you know
unity has a very simple
i guess
knowledge cost to getting started with
somebody who wants to write a game
because
they had some familiarity with with c
sharp where you know they had never read
written c plus before so you know that
that sort of took unreal out of the
equation you know so they were
interested in all right let's build a
game and then you know well all right if
we're going to build a game how are we
going to test the game because they were
both of them were for you know the
testing side of things of enterprise
software so you know they're already
thinking ahead and they're like well
you know what are our options and that
sort of led to the you know the birth of
game driver
and you know when shane asked me you
know if i wanted to be a part of this
and as you know we would start with
unity first and
i think he chose unity because he was
interested in doing game development
with it and that's sort of well let's
start here and let's build a concrete
product before we try to expand so
that's kind of how unity was happened to
be chosen as the you know the first
target of our product
can you speak a little bit to
multi-platform testing i know that unity
runs on many different platforms
including
mobile where would you recommend a
developer runs the automated tests do
they have to test on every platform they
ship on what platforms does game drivers
support just give us a picture of i'm
writing a game that runs on many
platforms how do i test it you know at
the end of the day
running your automated tests on windows
for instance is only going to give you
so much validation game driver has the
ability to be deployed on android and
ios devices so that you can interact
with those tests we have support for
some device farms as well so if a
developer doesn't have an android device
on him and he wants to run an automated
test he can you know spin up a device on
the device farm
and run his test you know if you're
targeting a platform you need to make
sure that it's being tested on if you
weren't let's pretend you weren't doing
automated testing you're not going to
deploy a game or an application on a
device without it being manually tested
so
anywhere we're manually testing
we need to see how we can introduce
automated testing to help facilitate you
know that test load and again
add all the benefits of doing automated
testing to begin with so you know we
support
windows mac linux is coming android
iphone ios platform
we are also starting to move into the
console market where unity is supported
switch is being targeted xbox is being
targeted and hopefully
sony will be targeted in the future
you talked about writing that first test
the first automated test
in sort of a generic way but with
gamedriver can you walk me through in
whatever details appropriate for this
conversation walk me through
how i would add that test and
maybe there's a tutorial online for more
details
yeah sure so the first thing would be
installing the unity package so we have
you know your standard plug-in type
unity package you import the package
into your unity game
create a new game object which is going
to host the game driver component then
add the script component for game driver
that's now listed in your your script
drop down
once that's there spin up uh instance of
visual studio or writer whichever you
want now i like to you know if we're
writing test cases you know we're going
to use a testing frame like in unit but
i like to keep it even simpler let's
create a console application in visual
studio or writer whatever
all right first thing we do add the
required references for game driver so i
think there's maybe four references that
need to be added
instantiate you know add the using
statement at the top again we're all
c-sharp here at the using statement
instantiate the api client you know with
the new empty constructor
add a connect statement all right we're
going to connect to
our local host
on a predefined port that is configured
in the agent we'll use our our default
port
all right we're connected all right
let's wait for an object
all right so the first thing we're going
to do is add an api wait for object so
if again our start screen is coming up
we want to wait for the start button to
be visible before you click it or hit
enter or whatever
so we've created which we actually have
a patent technology which is called
hierarchy path so hierarchy path is very
similar to xpath but allows us to
reference
objects in the unity gain tree
by you know a stringed path very similar
to xpath this allows
testers to write tests in a way that
aren't relying on coordinates and aren't
necessarily relying on
the exact structure of the tree not to
change so you know if our start button
was in the root but you know we
refactored some things and now it's you
know embedded down into the a couple
canvas layers or something like that the
tester can still execute the same test
over and over so we would you know write
we also have a plug-in for that as well
to create some rudimentary hierarchy
paths for an object that you select in
the tree so we you know we get the
hierarchy path for our start button we
do our you know our client dot wait for
object pass in the hierarchy path and
then you know we'll do a client
disconnect and you know boom there's
your first test case so we've created a
simple console application that connects
waits for the object and then
disconnects
so you mentioned your hierarchy paths
are similar to xpath can you remind me
what xpath is yeah so xpath is you know
let's say we have an xml document which
is a you know node leaf tree structure
we have attributes assigned to these
different nodes or the nodes have you
know names themselves so if we are
looking for a node that has a tag called
button you know we could simply
hit you know
forward slash forward slash button and
it's going to go down through the tree
you know wherever it is and it's going
to look for
a relative path of an element that has
the tag button and
that's the object we want to work with
so if you know
you move that start button down
you know 10 pixels or whatever it
doesn't matter if you move that button
anywhere else in the object tree it
doesn't matter we're still going to find
that
one of the first things people always
bring up when we're you know we're
demoing higher the game driver is like
well
what if you have a massive tree this is
going to be slow
well
slow relative maybe but again we're
doing automated testing it's not like
we're inserting plug-ins that are trying
to reach frames per second on test we're
executing a test case you know if it
takes
you know three 400 milliseconds to
identify that object you know okay it is
what it is but we're able to achieve our
our impending goal of performing an
action and validating the result of that
that's interesting you compare it to an
xml document so i know in unity and
other game engines you end up with a
hierarchy which is kind of the world and
the levels and the things in the world
and so
you're talking about navigating that
hierarchy
what does it mean to interrogate the
game i saw that reference is that
reflection or is that making calls to an
api that the game provides what's
interrogation in your in game driver
terminology yeah it could be both of
those things so reflection is a very
powerful thing and you know you get it
for free in unity and that's great for
our product
so you know if you need to look at a
specific value of a component you know
you can get it fairly easily and we can
test against that
if you want to write
specific code that you want to execute
that does something even more complex
then you know we can still call those
methods you know from the api client so
you're you can have a mix of that if you
want to embed a bunch of debug code and
execute it not a problem if you don't
want to do that and you want to still
introspect variables at different times
doing different things or or flag when
that hits a value you know all those
things are possible another term you
used a little bit ago was n-unit i think
that's the dot-net
version of j-unit or variation of j-unit
so i wanted to mention a previous
episode here episode 167 the history of
j unit and the future of testing with
kent beck i think that might be an
interesting background for this so you
talked about creating a
console application that runs a game
driver test then
at what point would you recommend using
a framework like end unit and what are
the advantages of a framework with game
driver you know the console is a very
simple let's just make it work let's not
add the complexity of setting up an end
unit with you know start up and tear
down fixtures and and all that
complexity let's just keep it simple
with the console application but you
know once you've made that work all
right now it's time to actually migrate
to a real testing framework so we you
know we're talking about end unit which
we create tutorials off of as well but
in reality you can you can use any
testing framework because ultimately
we're you know we're instantiating the
game game driver api client and we're
we're executing things whatever things
is so we can use any test framework to
do that
but you know once you
got the basics and established that you
can connect and do something all right
now it's time to start rolling this into
a testing framework like in unit for
example and
start building real test cases
so i think we've got things started
we've added tests we've added the
testing framework let's talk a little
bit more just some details about game
driver or some situations i might run
into if i'm a developer using game
driver so you mentioned screenshots on
errors but what about recording and
playback in general is that part of
some tests or all tests what what's the
role of recording in playing playback of
gameplay
we're about to release i guess probably
a beta version of our recording tool now
what is a recording tool all right so
recording and this goes back to even
application testing
the ability to record and just play back
specifics
is that there's so many variables and
when you introduce game you know games
in general into it you're adding massive
more variables so the reality is that
you're never going to have a simple
record something and
play it back with you know
a hundred percent that it's always going
to be reliable you know you're always
going to have to work off of it so what
what does recording add well recording
adds you the ability to have a
a starting structure of your test case
so you know you don't have to
figure out all the minor details via
code you can create a scaffolding
of your test case
so
you know you can record
your flow of what you're testing you're
moving through the game at a specific
point we can record that all right now
you can take that all right how do we
make this a repeatable test you know
let's add some weight statements here so
that we're waiting for specific actions
or objects to have certain values before
we move through in our test case and
coming back to where we started you know
how are manual testers going to do this
well it's
as you've seen you know if you want to
empower manual testers and test
automation engineers they're going to
need to know more about the game just
handing them a
running game is not necessarily going to
be sufficient for them to be able to
understand how to automate the testing
of that game now if that happens via you
know documentation and information
sharing or they actually have the game
running in unity so that they can learn
more about how to test that game
you know that's going to vary between
development studios i read that game
driver can run tests faster or slower
than real time
in practice do people tend to run tests
at the fastest possible speed or how
would you recommend people set the speed
of their tests
i think keeping your your test cases at
real time
has advantages of you know
you never know what's what could be
introduced that could cause you know
defects that aren't really defects so
you know the beauty of of automated
testing is you know it's
it's not just during working hours you
know you can you can run these things 24
7. so
the
the time criticalness of
executing something faster than needs to
be tested is
is probably less of a moot point i mean
you could
if you need to run tests twice as fast
well spin up two nodes of you know two
jenkins agents that are kicking off your
test
simultaneously so i think that's you
know
it's kind of a moot point you know
whether we need to execute faster or
slower
how about reusable functionality i guess
you mentioned end units test fixtures
maybe that's the answer but suppose i
have a series of tests that i'll need to
start with some common functionality
some common steps is that something that
gamedriver
helps you with or or is the testing
framework how you do that again game
driver is just a tool it's not it's not
your testing framework so we're building
a framework you know maybe we have a set
of code of how we start our game
and we need to execute that in all of
our tests if we're shutting down the
game each time so you're gonna create
your own sort of testing framework of of
how you use game driver to interact with
with your particular game or product
okay and some couple more kind of
detailed questions
one build method with unity is called
ilcpp where the
c sharp is converted to c plus plus and
then compiled to a to a binary so in
that case it's not running
dot net i guess
not in the normal way
do you run your tests compiled down to c
plus for a game or would you want to run
that in c sharp mode
it's funny you bring that up because
that's been the bane of many headaches
for myself
as far as a from a development
perspective but when we do our our own
testing of of our product we
support all
lts versions of unity so you know we've
got to test
you know 2019 2020 and now 2021 we test
on windows mac android ios and we test
all of those against using mono or you
know the net or and we test against the
il-2 cpp to make sure that is working
because you know
if companies are building their product
to run off of il to cpp we want to make
sure that they're able to actually
automate and test with our product on
those builds as well
okay yeah that's a lot of configurations
to test
how about the new input system versus
the classic input manager in unity is
there anything to say there relative to
game driver or is that just a detail
that the games can use either one
so
we you know for a quite a period of time
where you know you could go on and you
could search about it on you know
you know google unity new input system
and you know if you look back in like
2020 maybe you know there's tons of
posts where people like all this thing
is terrible it's slow it doesn't work
and that was probably like version
0.2 or something like that i can't
remember their versioning information
but now you know they're at version 1.3
and
i think it's 1.3 and it's you know
you've got all these people in the
community who are writing blog posts all
right here's how you use the new input
system
and only recently have we started
working on support for that so it's uh
while it has some of its own challenges
that we're addressing you know there
it's a con pro for on both sides where
implementing some of the game driver
functionality for the old versus the new
was more difficult than the other but
you know how we're supporting it and
ultimately you know it we want it to be
you know no fuss no muss are you using
the old input system great are you using
the new input system no problem are
using a mix of them no problem you know
we're working to support those we're
also looking at how now that we've added
support for these
are we going to support things like
rewired or are we going to create some
kind of sdk interface that lets people
build out that compatibility no matter
what input manager they're using whether
they choose to use
unities or something like rewireds or
they build their own you know how can we
still enable these people to to test
their their game and application as i
said earlier you know uh
critical things
user input
and validation of you know
the result of your of your tests so we
need to make sure that we're able to
provide support for
the test user input whatever that is let
me just flag one thing you mentioned
rewired is that a company or what is
that anything i can't tell you a whole
lot about it but it's just a product
slash maybe the same maybe company as
well
i can't remember but they created their
own input manager where you know their
selling point is
easily switch between you know keyboard
mouse
nintendo switch controller playstation
any device easily you know maybe they
have maybe they have better performance
than the unity input manager uh
i can't comment on the you know the
selling points of it but just other than
the fact that we've looked into it
whether you know
need and how to support it
okay we've talked about adding game
driver we've talked about some specific
details if i'm using game driver let's
start wrapping up
today i think game driver is exclusively
for unity what other game engines are
you planning to support and what is the
timetable for those
we've got two ongoing ports
one is
godot we're working on building an
initial version of that i did a proof of
concept for godot maybe
maybe a year and a half ago just to you
know
prove it out see how much you know
product reuse we would have between the
two
so we're moving moving forward with that
because we want to be able to you know
offer a you know we've got a
what i would classify as a community
engine and we want to we would think it
would be nice to be able to support that
and we're also working on an unreal port
as well so
we did a proof of concept with that
september last year around there i did a
proof of concept for it so
you've got a c-sharp engine and
well you know exposed c-sharp and unity
and c plus plus for unreal and so
there's quite a bit of difference in
how do we add value and again how do we
be a light footprint for developers who
want to add it to their game so there's
there's still a lot of thought there but
you know we're we're actively moving
forward with that and we want to
continue to build out the um on the
console market as well and
we want to be synonymous with with game
testing you know whether you wrote
whether you were hard to write automated
tests on unity and then you know you
move to an unreal project we want to we
want to empower those people to be able
to to do both
you know it's job stability for people
you know let's
how do we help people
so godot is a open source game engine in
unreal is sort of the second or first
less second big commercial game engine
do you have a sense for how many
companies you are working with have
already embraced automated testing and
they're just looking for a way to do it
or is part of your sales cycle to
convince companies that automated
testing is worthwhile in the first place
my personal
thoughts are that
automated testing has been around you
know for so long
you would be hard-pressed to find
anybody in technology who doesn't know
what automated testing is
that's not the hard sell the hard sell
is they're thinking yes we need to do
this how do we do this
all right we're gonna have to allocate
you know somebody to look at this
somebody and investigate it it's like
it's that speed bump we need to get them
over you know you know we're trying to
build out more educational material you
know training quick start guides
something that allows that you know that
speed bump you know not to look like a
mountain but to look like a speed bump
where
you're gonna have to allocate a resource
to to look into this and to use it so
it's
you know it's a project planning and how
do we make it work it's just you know
helping people feel comfortable
that
one it's not a huge time sink to even
get started which it's not so
for me it's a it feels like an easy sell
but you know it's
there's a lot of things going on and on
their side of things that we don't see
but
i think you know everybody is on board
for automated testing it's just you know
how do we get them started
how about what developments do you see
in automated testing beyond games or in
games sort of what developments are you
looking at which might impact your
business and the developers in the next
couple years anything coming along
i think it's
you know it's understanding the troubles
that developers are seeing now you know
issues that developers had to deal with
in the past
are are changing you know
maybe there were you know they were
using in-house engines and
that created its own issues and now
they're moving to commercial engines
like unreal and unity and so now they're
dealing with different issues so how do
we modify and continue to adapt our
product so that we can help them solve
their new challenges
with whatever that might be in the in
the future
so i think we're done is there anything
else you'd like to add that we didn't
cover today and how can people get in
touch with you and learn more about game
driver or contact you
we're always interested to you know talk
to anybody as a friend of mine says you
know i'll talk to anybody so if you're
if you have questions or you're
interested or you know your professor is
teaching testing and you want to learn
how to you know
teach your kids about game driver or you
know just testing in general you know
we're happy to meet we're happy to talk
with anybody can reach us you know
through our contact information on our
website
gamedriver.io and we wish everybody
happy happy testing going forward and
you know we hope you'll embrace the
the continued revolution of automated
testing
thank you that's a good place to end and
i will put some links in the show notes
for more information
this is philip winston for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening